Donald De Lue Papers
Donald De Lue Papers
1941-1965
De Lue, Donald, 1897-1988.
3 linear ft.
Papers of the American sculptor. Incoming and outgoing correspondence (1957-1964); photographs of work (1941-1965); published material by and about De Lue; and 3 sketches (circa 1954).
148936
Biographical History
Donald De Lue (1897-1988) was an American sculptor and medallist. Born in Boston, Massachusetts, he studied at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts and spent several years in Paris. He is perhaps best known for his 45-foot high sculpture of the "Rocket Thrower," commissioned for and exhibited at the New York World's Fair in the Plaza of the Astronauts. This figure is familiar not only to those who have visited the Fair but to people all over the world, as it was reproduced in the official World's Fair postage stamp.
De Lue lived in Leonardo, New Jersey for much of his career but maintained a studio in New York City. He taught at the Beaux-Arts Institute of Design in New York City during the early 1940s. He also did work for the Boy Scouts of America, Carnegie Technical Institute, the United States Naval Academy, and West Point Academy, and served as Advance Editor for American Artist Magazine and as Chairman of the Hall of Fame for Great Americans at New York University.
Over his career he received numerous recognitions, including a Guggenheim Fellowship from the National Institute of Arts and Letters and several gold medals, one from the Architectural League and one from the National Sculpture Association. In 1960 he won two Henry Hering Awards (given by the National Sculpture Society) for his Omaha Beach Memorial in Normandy, France and for the Stations of the Cross at the Loyola Jesuit Seminary in Shrub Oak, New York. In 1967, De Lue won the American Numismatic Society's Saltus Award for Outstanding Achievement in the Art of the Medal.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Donald De Lue Papers consist of correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, published materials and sketches.
Correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing. Subject files consists of a few dedications but mostly of photographs of Mr. De Lue and his work.
Manuscripts contain one paper written by Mr. De Lue. Published material includes books, magazine articles and newspaper clippings about Mr. De Lue and his work, magazine articles and a book review by him, pamphlets about his work and a postage stamp with his work represented on it. Sketches includes three pencil sketch studies on illustration board (circa 1954).
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is subdivided into incoming and outgoing; incoming is arranged alphabetically by author, outgoing is arranged chronologically. Subject files and Published material are arranged alphabetically by type, and then (where possible) in chronological order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; De Lue, Donald, 1897-1988.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Sketches.; Artists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Donald De Lue.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, H and N, 1960; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Outgoing, 1957; 1964 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Dedications, 1957; 1960,; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of, 1941; 1947,; 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Studio Interiors, 1959; 1961,; undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs of work
    - Brookgreen Gardens, South Carolina, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Chapels at West Point and Arlington, Virginia, undated (Box 1)
    - Chemistry Building, University of Pennsylvania, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Christian Herald Building, New York City, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Edward Hull Crump Memorial, undated (Box 1)
    - Federal Court House, Philadelphia, undated (Box 1)
    - Federal Reserve Bank, Boston, undated (Box 1)
    - Federal Reserve Bank, Philadelphia, undated (Box 1)
    - Harvey Firestone Memorial, 1950; undated (Box 1)
    - Germantown Jewish Center, Philadelphia, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Junior High School, New York City, undated (Box 1)
    - Interchurch Center, New York City, undated (Box 1)
    - Memorial Chapel, Virginia Polytechnic Institute, undated (Box 1)
    - New Orleans Civic Center, 1960 (Box 1)
    - New York World's Fair, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Portraits of others, 1943; 1960,; 1962,; undated (Box 1)
    - Relief frieze, unidentified (Oversize 2)
    - Reliefs for medals, 1945; 1961,; undated (Box 1)
    - Science and Engineering Building, Carnegie Technical Institute, undated (Box 1)
    - Sisters of St. Joseph, Toronto, Canada, undated (Box 1)
    - United States Cemetery Memorial, St. Laurent, Sur-mer-France, undated (Box 1)
    - United States Military Cemetery Memorial, St. Laurent, Normandy, France, 1957; 1963,; undated (Box 1)
    - United States Naval Academy, 1956; undated (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - "The Word of the Lord Endureth Forever, " about De Lue, 1963 (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Books about, 1955-1957; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
  - Books by others: “Myself to Clarify – a saga in sements” by Hardwick Nevin, with drawings by Donald De Lue, self published book of poetry with inscription by the author to De Lue (Box 1)
  - Book review by, in National Sculpture, v.8 no.3, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Magazine articles by, 1957; 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    AIA: Journal of the American Institute of Architects, v.28 no.3, July 1957; National Sculpture Review, v.12 no.3, Fall 1963; This Week, Jan 21, 1962
  - Magazine articles about, 1951; 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    American Artist, v.15 no.1, Jan 1951; v.15 no.9 Nov 1951; v.28 no.6, June 1964; National Sculpture Review, v.2 no.2, Spring 1953; Temas Revista Ilustrada, v.2, no.81, Junio 1951
  - Magazine articles about others, 1965 (Box 1)
    American Art and Stone, v.65 no.2, Feb 1965; Empire State Mason, v.9 no.6, Jan 1962
  - Magazines with reproductions of De Lue's art
    - National Sculpture Review, 1952-1964; 2 folders (Box 1)
      v.1 no. 3, June 1952; v.2 no.4, fall 1953; v.3 no.4, fall 1954 (2 copies); v.4 no.1, winter 1954/1955; v.4 no.2, spring 1955; v.4 no.4, winter 1955; v.5 no.3, fall 1956; [as National Sculpture Society Review] v.5 no. 4, winter 1955/1956; v.6 no.3, fall 1957; v.6 no.4, winter 1957/58; v.7 no.2, summer 1958; v.7 no.4, winter 1958; v.8 no.1, spring 1959 v.9 no.1, spring 1960 v.9 no.4, winter 1960/61 v.10 no.1, spring 1961 v.10 no.3, fall 1961 v.10 no.4, winter 1961/62 v.11 no.1, spring 1962 v.11 no.3, fall 1962 v.13 no.2, summer 1964
    - Miscellaneous, 1957-1964; 2 folders (Box 2)
      American Art in Stone, v.57 no.6, June 1957 & v.59 no.9, Sep 1959 American Artist, v.21 no.8, Oct 1957; American Mercury, v.87, Oct 1958 (cover only); Art News, v.63 no.4, summer 1964; Empire State Mason, v.9 no.6, Jan 1962, & v.11 no.5, Nov/Dec 1963; The General Magazine and Hiftorical Chronicle, v.58 nos.3/4, spring/summer 1956; Indiana Freemason, v.35 no.1, June 1957; Intercollegian, v.70 no.8, Apr 1953; National Geographic Magazine, v.111 no.6, June 1957; New Hampshire Churchman, v.10 no.3, Mar 1957; Techgram, v.37 no.18, June 15, 1960 (includes "Memorial Supplement" of De Lue’s Memorial Court at Virginia Polytechnic Institute
    - Miscellaneous, 1953; 1955 (Oversize 2)
      Buffalo Courier Express Pictorial, Sun Apr 3, 1955; Philadelphia Inquirer Magazine, Apr 3, 1955; Pioneer Magazine (St. Paul Sunday Pioneer Press), Apr 3, 1955; Sunday News, New York’s Picture Newspaper, June 7, 1953; Washington Star Pictorial Magazine, June 7, 1953
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings about, 1941-1947; 1950-1959,; 1963,; undated (Oversize 2)
  - Pamphlets, 1953-1954; 1960 (Box 2)
  - Postage stamp, New York World’s Fair, 1964-1965; U. S. Postage 5¢, on board with description of De Lue’s sculpture, with signature (Box 2)
- Sketches
  - Untitled sketch, Moses seated with tablets; graphite on trace paper mounted on illustration board, 12 x 23 in. (Oversize 1)
  - Untitled sketch, Moses standing with tablets; graphite on trace paper mounted on illustration board, 13 x 23 in.; first studies for VPI, Virgina, written on verso (Oversize 1)
  - Untitled sketch, 1954; female figure with sword; graphite on illustration board, 6 x 19 in. (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)